[Music]
so with 2024 release Wave 2 business
Central can notify uh users in product
or help admin help administrators
orchestrate notifications when critical
business processes or critical
background processing stops for some
reason I'm even colage and I'm a product
manager in business Central engineering
team and I hope you can join me for the
next couple of minutes to see these new
capabilities in action so sometimes
tasks reports or batch processes take
longer to complete to keep people
productive while these uh while these
things are happening companies often use
business centrals uh job queue uh to run
the processes in the background of
course it's something something goes
wrong and it's important or an important
background process stops or it isn't
scheduled for some reason being notified
about such situations can help you react
quickly and resolve the
issues so let's see how we can set up
the job Q notifications to help us with
that in action to set up job Q
notifications all you need to do is go
to assisted setup and find setup job Q
notifications assisted setup
guide and follow a couple of steps to
set it up when you start the job C
notifications uh setup you will uh pick
who you want to be notified when the
background tasks uh either fail or stop
for some reason there are two options
available in here as any user can uh
initiate the background task you can
just uh toggle this uh button in here to
notify only sort of the owner who run
who ran that task apart from that you
can also uh choose to uh notified what
we call Job Q notification
administrators I mean these are not real
administrators but you could say that uh
you can have a department head or it
admin or somebody who has an interest of
uh getting notified when uh some of
these things U uh some of these uh
things fail for some reason so this is
done to reduce the noise um uh to the
regular users of notifications so
there's way there's bit more control uh
that you can have uh in in these
notifications so if you decide that you
want to U notify not only the person who
has initiated the background task but
you want to notify somebody else you can
always say I will add this person in
here and for example I will have uh my
boss uh get notified as soon as some of
the tasks that I have uh run uh fails
because it could be a business critical
process that is running in the
background click clicking next so what
you can see on this screen is that you
can set notification you can Define how
you want to notify users and there are
two options which can be used either
together or um one by one first one is
in product notifications which is pretty
self-explanatory so users get
notifications while they are in the
product and the other one is you can
actually orchestrate the the
notifications uh to get to your users
even when they are not using the product
right and is done uh through the use of
uh external business events this part of
the feature is uh currently in preview
mainly because the business events are
uh still in preview and we are taking
dependency on that so let me turn uh
both of these on and simply click next
the next screen actually shows you how
frequently you want to be notified when
such situations happen you can set it up
to get notified immediately or you can
actually go and specify a threshold and
say if this is a job queue that handles
some um some integration with a third
party service it can happen that uh some
of the some of the issues that might
occur might occur because the the third
party servic is unavailable or something
happened in there and it just makes
sense to retry a couple of more times
and these these are not these are sort
of transient issues right and for these
kinds of things you might not want to to
get notified uh every single time so
what you can specify in here you can say
oh well you know um if this thing
actually fails you know three to five
times then go ahead and uh and notify me
and clicking next actually finishes up
the the setup of the job Q
notifications so to recap the demo what
you saw is basically the the assisted
setup guide takes you through three
steps you basically say who you want to
notify whether it's a user who ran the
job or it's a job queue administrator or
people in the list that uh that will get
notified for every failure you select
how you want to notify user whether it's
in product or uh externally through
external business using external
business events or and the last thing
that you can that you saw in the demo is
U that you can actually pick the
frequency of notifications
and you can choose whether to have them
U show up immediately or when specific
thresholds uh are
reached getting in product notifications
about issues uh with job geue background
processing is a thing that I want to
show you uh next so let's switch over to
the demo and show you uh in product
notifications in action the moment the
user logs in uh its assigned role Center
the thing that he will see if there are
U background processing tasks that uh
failed for some reason or have
experienced an issue is this
notification strip so the thing that he
can do is uh he can always go ahead and
say show more details and this actually
lists uh list the the the job cues that
have uh failed for some reason in
process you can see all of them are in
error State and the user can go and
inspect uh the details of of these
things uh further on by like showing an
error or restarting the job manually in
here another thing that you saw on the
notification was it it actually had that
action that says don't show this again
so each and every user can after initial
setup go to my setting and change the
notifications that they want to uh
receive so admin has through the job que
notification setup what the admin did
was was made sure that all of the users
if if he has picked that option to to
notify the users that are
initiating uh job cues all of the users
in my notification page uh got this
enabled uh toggle enabled for the job
que notification in here of course any
user who is not interested in that or
who is not working with background
processing can always uh turn this thing
off the another interesting thing is
that uh what the regular user um sees in
the role Center are also three
additional cues that talk about uh job Q
tasks so he can see uh tasks failed he
can see tasks that are in progress and
he can see tasks that are sort of
pending or that are waiting to be uh
waiting to be
executed and if you look at the Q setup
in here you can actually see that you
know three and five uh thresholds that
the admin has set up in through the job
Q notification assisted setup guide so
these were the thresholds that got
copied and applied again to each users's
uh uh to each users's uh queue setup to
uh color the queue as you can see this
task failed uh Q got colored as uh as
red because the number of uh the number
of uh job cues that failed is now three
and of course that that gives me also
the visual ual indication in case I've
missed that uh in case I've missed that
notification uh on the
top another thing that is uh specific um
for for the job C tasks uh uh part of
the role Center it always shows only the
uh the information that is specific to
the user that has signed in which is
different for the users that you have uh
specified as a job Q notification admins
those
users those users uh see uh their own uh
job queue tasks so the job cues that
they have run but they can also see and
access the the job cues uh the the job
cues and the job CU statuses of the
other users so let me show you that in a
uh another role Center for another user
now I've logged in as one of the job
queue notification admin ad
ministrators and as you can see I'm in a
in a different Ro Center and I also get
a notification for the job cues that are
experiencing an issue but as I said
before as you if if you look at the list
of the job queue U entries that are
shown in my queue uh for the for the
failed uh job cues you can see that I
can actually see job cues from uh from
different
users and that wraps uh wraps up this in
product notifications uh demo let's
switch back to the
deck so in the in product notifications
demo what you saw is a different
experience for the user and different
experience for the job Q uh
administrator the major difference being
uh that that part of the demo that
showed it for the regular users actually
shows uh the regular user a their own uh
job C task in their own uh role Center
it shows how they can um sort of tweak
the the level of notifications either
through my notifications or through uh
setting up different thresholds uh for
for the
jobs which brings us uh to
a uh the the the next way of uh getting
notified about uh job queue entries and
that's using these external
notifications with business events we do
have users that do not live in uh
business Central like the most of the
regular users but admins have you know
sort of seldomly access uh business
Central when they need to assign
permissions or do various administrative
task so it is of utmost importance that
we also provide uh some information to
uh such users when they are not signed
in in business Central so let me show
you how you can actually uh orchestrate
the notifications using the business
center
events and power automate so let's see
that in
action so the other way to uh set up
this external notifications is through
orchestrating this uh using business
events and power automate so we'll go to
the job que entries and in here we will
look for a famous automate uh menu where
I will pick create an automated
flow and I will search for J Q
template like I have as you can see we
now have a uh new power automate
template that can be used to uh
orchestrate this external notification
this particular one will send an email
to uh Outlook when the job queue fails
so we'll set up a uh connection to
business Central and to
Outlook click
next we will also pick the environment
and we will pick the
company and optionally in here you can
specify uh who else you want to have
copied this could be particularly useful
if you have a partner team that is also
interested in receiving such
notifications for for specific uh for
specific business critical uh uh job
cues I'll leave that one blank and
create a flow
all right let's examine that flow in
power automate okay and here we are in
power automate where we have a flow
created based on the template and the
parameters that we've uh specified as
you can see the template created a flow
by filling in uh all the details and
parameters that we've uh set up and
eventually what we should uh get is an
email uh looking like this when a job
queue fails the last thing that uh we
need to do in here we can try try out uh
this
template so let's switch back to
business Central and see if we can
simulate uh one job C failing I see that
there is a purchase posting that has
been failing so I can probably simulate
that one in uh in business Central once
more so I'll go to purchase
invoices and I will just run because I
have the background posting set I will
run the background posting and as you
can see uh they have been scheduled for
posting and they will eventually
fail so let me switch to uh Outlook to
see if I got the
notification and as you can see uh in
Outlook I Got a notification that a
purchase U documents posting has failed
it has been scheduled by me in this
company I have the link to a uh job Q
entry page and job q log entry page as
well as some additional details about
the environment about tenant ID and
about the error message which turns out
that I'm I was missing just a vendor
invoice number in this job queue and
that was the reason why it failed so
what you saw in the previous demo was
how easy it is actually to uh
orchestrate these external notifications
with any of the connectors that power
automate offers and all of this has
actually been uh made available by a
couple of uh new additions in business
Central so we've added a couple of job Q
apis to support us with that we have an
we now have an API for job queue entry
that has a restart bound action that you
can call automatically from uh from flow
so you can one could easily imagine a
sort of teams notifications with a
adaptive card uh that is shown to the
admin that can just that just needs to
click restart when he sees that this is
you know maybe some transient issue for
the for the job Q entry then there is a
job q log entries uh API and of course
there's a job queue task failed business
event uh that have actually made all of
these
uh external notifications uh available
Plus on top of that as I as I said you
have a power automate uh template that
is available in business Central uh
Gallery right now that you can just use
and slightly adjust to fit your needs to
enable the external uh
notifications and with that um I hope
you enjoyed the video uh I urge you to
uh try out uh this uh new new impr
movements uh that we've made in job Q
notifications be sure to send us
feedback about that and also make sure
to check out the description uh of the
video that is below the video together
with uh some additional useful links
thank you for your time